Guide to the Ina Clausen Papers BCMS.0015
Brooklyn Collection
Ina Clausen Papers
1943-1973
1966-1973
Brooklyn Collection
Clausen, Ina, 1943-
BCMS.0015
0.42 Linear feet in 1 document box and 1 oversize folder
Brooklynite Ina Clausen co-founded a women's collective print shop in the late 1960s. This collection consists of her personal papers as well as records from the Greenpoint Print Shop and copies of feminist writings and publications to which Clausen contributed.
Scope and Contents
The first series of the Ina Clausen Papers collection contains personal records from Clausen's early life in Brooklyn, NY, including school report cards, church certificates, family photographs, and publications Clausen contributed to at her high school, Prospect Heights High School. The second series consists of an assortment of flyers, greeting cards, raffle tickets and invitations produced by the Greenpoint Print Shop, of which Clausen was a founding member. Also included are the letters of resignation from this organization's executive staff. The third series is comprised of Feminist journals Clausen contributed to, as well as rough drafts of an article Clausen published in the journal Up from Under.
Biographical Note
Ina Clausen was born February 21, 1943 to Einar Clausen and Linda Hansen Clausen in Brooklyn, NY. She attended the Prospect Heights High School, where she was on the art staff of her high school's publication, the Cardinal. Clausen graduated in 1960.
In the late 1960s Clausen co-founded a women's collective print shop at 573 Metropolitan Avenue in Brooklyn. Fellow founders included Nina Hutchinson, Linda Feldman, Barbara Kaminsky, Karen Ninnis, Alice Moffett, Page Dougherty, Hazel Doren, and Alice Appleton. The shop was called the Greenpoint Print Shop, and was supported from donations of equipment from David Dellinger, who published Liberation Magazine in New Jersey. At the print shop Clausen designed and printed materials for several local activist groups, including the Southern Conference Educational Fund, the Southside Community of Greenpoint, the National Association for Irish Freedom, Yellow Pearl (an Asian-American organization based in Chinatown), Los Tintos Indios, a Red Hook, Brooklyn-based Puerto Rican group, and several women's liberation groups.
Clausen served as president of the Greenpoint Print Shop until late 1972, when she and the other officers all resigned and turned the corporation over to another group. During this period and beyond, Clausen participated in local activistorganizations, including the Flatbush Committee to End the War in Vietnam. She also designed and published informational packets to educate women about the Women's Liberation Movement. Her work in this movement included contributions to the Feminist journal, Up from Under, which focused on working women.
Access
Collection is located in the Brooklyn Collection at the Central Branch at Grand Army Plaza. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Use
While many items in the Brooklyn Collection are unrestricted, we do not own reproduction rights to all materials. Be aware of the several kinds of rights that might apply: copyright, licensing and trademarks. The borrower assumes all responsibility for copyright questions.
Provenance
Gift from Ina Clausen, September 2008.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series by type.
Series I: Personal Records and Correspondence
Series II: Greenpoint Print Shop Papers
Series III: Feminist Writings and Publications
Feminism -- United States; Greenpoint (New York, N.Y.); Print shops (Printing industry); United States -- New York (State) -- New York -- Brooklyn
- Series I: Personal Records and Correspondence, 1944-1966
  - Baptism and Sunday School Certificates, 1943-1951. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Program and certificate for "Prize Baby Show", 1944. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Report cards, P.S. 246 and P.S. 181, 1949-1952. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Prospect Heights High School Cardinal Special, c. late-1950's. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Prospect Heights High School Cardinal, Literary Art Issue, 1959. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Prospect Heights High School Cardinal Senior Issue (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter to Robert Clausen, from Ralph., 1966. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Family photographs (includes CD-R), 1946-1968. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Church pins, c. 1950's. (Box 1)
  - Girl Scout pins, c. 1950's. (Box 1)
- Series II: Greenpoint Print Shop Papers, 1966-1973
  - Small flyers and raffle tickets, c. early 1970s. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Flatbush Committee to End the War in Vietnam flyers, 1966-1968. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Peace and Freedom Party flyers, late 1960s. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom and subgroups flyers, 1971-1973 (1 of 2). (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom and subgroups flyers, 1971-1973 (2 of 2). (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Greetings cards for Southern Conference Educational Fund and Little People's Nursery, c. early 1970s. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Various flyers, c. early 1970s. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters of resignation from officers and stationery, 1972. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Mayor Lindsay Help Save Our Homes" oversize flyer, c. early 1970s. (Folder Ephemera OS 3)
    General
    Note: This item is located in the Ephemera collection, oversize box 3.
- Series III: Feminist Writings and Publications, 1970-1973
  - Feelings from Women's Liberation #1, c. early 1970s. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Envelope and article packet, Women's Liberation, c. early 1970s. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Up from Under, by, for, and about women, vol. 1, no. 1, 1970. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Up from Under, vol. 1, no. 2, 1970. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Transcript and notes for interview with Woolworth's employee, 1971. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Up from Under, vol. 1, no. 3, 1971. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Up from Under, vol. 1, no. 4, 1971. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Up from Under, vol. 1, no. 5, 1973. (Box 1, Folder 24)